export const BIOLOGYA2016 = [

{
id: "question1",
question:  "1. An example of an organism that exists as a colony is",
A: "Spirogyra",
B: "Paramecium",
C: "Euglena",
D: "Volvox",
answer: "D. Volvox",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question2",
question:  "2. Gymnosperms bear naked seeds because they",
A: "ovary",
B: "colourful flowers",
C: "pollen grains",
D: "stigma",
answer: "A. ovary",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question3",
question:  "3. DNA formation is associated with",
A: "golgi bodies",
B: "lysosomes",
C: "mitochondria",
D: "nucleus",
answer: "D. nucleus",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question4",
question:  "4. The term that can be used to describe what happened to plant A after seven hours is",
A: "wilting",
B: "competition",
C: "transpiration",
D: "osmosis",
answer: "A. wilting",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question5",
question:  "5. The environmental factors responsible for the condition in plant B are",
A: "low humidity and low temperature",
B: "high humidity and low temperature",
C: "low humidity and high temperature",
D: "high humidity and high temperature",
answer: "C. low humidity and high temperature",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question6",
question:  "6. Hydra is considered to be at a tissue level of organization of life because it",
A: "has numerous cells that perform different functions",
B: "has developed organs and systems",
C: "has poorly developed nervous system",
D: "reproduces by budding",
answer: "A. has numerous cells that perform different functions",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question7",
question:  "7. Which of the following statements about the diagrams is correct?",
A: "They are both organs",
B: "One of them is an organism",
C: "They both form part of tissues",
D: "They are both harmful to humans",
answer: "C. They both form part of tissues",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question8",
question:  "8. A decrease in the number of II will result in",
A: "an increase in urine production",
B: "an increase in energy production",
C: "a decreased population",
D: "decreased immunity",
answer: "D. decreased immunity",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question9",
question:  "9. Flaccidity in plants is associated with",
A: "cessation of photosynthesis",
B: "wilting",
C: "turgidity",
D: "discolouration of leaves",
answer: "B. wilting",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question10",
question:  "10. Which of the following substances is not usually present in the urine of healthy person?",
A: "Urea",
B: "Mineral salts",
C: "Glucose",
D: "Water",
answer: "C. Glucose",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question11",
question:  "11. Muscles act in opposite directions in order to",
A: "cause a bone to move",
B: "prevent dislocation at joints",
C: "prevent muscle fatigue",
D: "regulate bodily activities",
answer: "A. cause a bone to move",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question12",
question:  "12. Lateral meristem in flowering plants is found in the",
A: "cortex",
B: "pericycle",
C: "cambium",
D: "pith",
answer: "C. cambium",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question13",
question:  "13. The cells and tissues of the nose, throat, chest diaphragm and lungs form the",
A: "circulatory system",
B: "respiratory system",
C: "transport system",
D: "digestive system",
answer: "B. respiratory system",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question14",
question:  "14. The exchange of gases between the environment and the respiratory organs of vertebrates is referred to as",
A: "inhalation",
B: "respiration",
C: "expiration",
D: "breathing",
answer: "D. breathing",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question15",
question:  "15. The maintenance of a constant internal environment in an organism is known as",
A: "homeostasis",
B: "homoiothermy",
C: "diuresis",
D: "dialysis",
answer: "A. homeostasis",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question16",
question:  "16. Which of the following organs is responsible for the production of insulin?",
A: "Spleen",
B: "Adrenal gland",
C: "Thyroid gland",
D: "Pancreas",
answer: "D. Pancreas",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question17",
question:  "17. Which of the following actions is not a voluntary action?",
A: "Stealing",
B: "Sneezing",
C: "Fighting",
D: "Cheating",
answer: "B. Sneezing",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question18",
question:  "18. In both dicotyledonous and monocotyledonous plants, the root hairs originate from the",
A: "piliferous layer",
B: "epidermal layer",
C: "endodermal layer",
D: "cortical layer",
answer: "A. piliferous layer",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question19",
question:  "19. Which of the following parts of the ear does not contain endolymph?",
A: "Semi-circular canals",
B: "Utriculus",
C: "Tympanum",
D: "Sacculus",
answer: "C. Tympanum",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question20",
question:  "20. The type of placentation illustrated in the diagram below is",
A: "marginal",
B: "parietal",
C: "axile",
D: "basal",
answer: "D. basal",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question21",
question:  "21. The correct order for the test is",
A: "I, II, III and IV",
B: "I, III, II and IV",
C: "II, III, I and IV",
D: "III, I, II, and IV",
answer: "D. III, I, II, and IV",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question22",
question:  "22. The best time to pluck the leaf for the experiment is",
A: "after being exposed to sunlight",
B: "three hours after sunset",
C: "before sunrise",
D: "six hours after sunset",
answer: "A. after being exposed to sunlight",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question23",
question:  "23. In which of the plant tissues are guard cells located?",
A: "Epidermis",
B: "Mesophyll",
C: "Vascular",
D: "Meristems",
answer: "A. Epidermis",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question24",
question:  "24. The association between two organisms in which one of the organism gains and the other loses is referred to as",
A: "saprophytism",
B: "commensalism",
C: "mutualism",
D: "parasitism",
answer: "D. parasitism",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question25",
question:  "25. The function of the villi in the alimentary canal is to",
A: "secrete gastric juice",
B: "curdle milk",
C: "emulsify fat",
D: "increase the surface area for absorption",
answer: "D. increase the surface area for absorption",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question26",
question:  "26. Which of the structures is not an organ of the digestive system",
A: "Oesophagus",
B: "Pancreas",
C: "Stomach",
D: "Kidney",
answer: "D. Kidney",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question27",
question:  "27. The source of nitrates in the part labelled I is the",
A: "root nodules of legumes",
B: "cloud",
C: "fertilizers",
D: "organic matter",
answer: "C. fertilizers",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question28",
question:  "28. The phenomenon in the diagram is termed",
A: "denitrification",
B: "conservation",
C: "eutrophication",
D: "global warming",
answer: "A. denitrification",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question29",
question:  "29. Another cause that could lead to phenomenon in the diagram is",
A: "exhaust from cars",
B: "oil spillage",
C: "dumping of sewage",
D: "excess rainfall",
answer: "C. dumping of sewage",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question30",
question:  "30. In ecology, a community refers to",
A: "a number of individuals of a given species",
B: "groups of different living in a habitat",
C: "existing species in an abandoned farmland",
D: "the dominant species in the habitat",
answer: "B. groups of different living in a habitat",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question31",
question:  "31. The direction of wind is determined by",
A: "an anemometer",
B: "a Secchi disc",
C: "a wind vane",
D: "a barometer",
answer: "C. a wind vane",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question32",
question:  "32. Food webs are complex because",
A: "the number of producers are large",
B: "many animals feed directly on producers",
C: "they include primary, secondary and tertiary consumers",
D: "some animals form part of several food chains",
answer: "D. some animals form part of several food chains",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question33",
question:  "33. Special modifications which enable an organism to survive in its habitat is known as",
A: "adaptation",
B: "tolerance",
C: "mimicry",
D: "colouration",
answer: "A. adaptation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question34",
question:  "34. Which of the following relationships does not involve two organism?",
A: "Commensalism",
B: "Saprophitism",
C: "Symbiotism",
D: "Parasitism",
answer: "B. Saprophitism",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question35",
question:  "35. Overcrowding in a population does not result in",
A: "death",
B: "commensalism",
C: "competition",
D: "migration",
answer: "B. commensalism",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question36",
question:  "36. A pandemic is an outbreak of diseases that",
A: "is confined to a town",
B: "is widespread",
C: "will not spread",
D: "has limited spread",
answer: "B. is widespread",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question37",
question:  "37. The rational and prudent use of natural resources is known as",
A: "preservation",
B: "conservation",
C: "utilization",
D: "management",
answer: "B. conservation",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question38",
question:  "38. Which of the following natural resources cannot be conserved?",
A: "Soil",
B: "Water",
C: "Wildlife",
D: "Air",
answer: "D. Air",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question39",
question:  "39. Which of the following actions supports conservation? To",
A: "protect endangered species",
B: "preserve trees for timber",
C: "permit hunting activities",
D: "provide income for the government",
answer: "A. protect endangered species",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question40",
question:  "40. A noticeable physical appearance of individuals of the same species is called",
A: "physical variation",
B: "physiological variation",
C: "morphological variation",
D: "discontinuous variation",
answer: "C. morphological variation",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question41",
question:  "41. A blend of inherited and acquired characteristics shows",
A: "variation",
B: "inheritance",
C: "evolution",
D: "heredity",
answer: "A. variation",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question42",
question:  "42. A cross between two parents produced four offspring with blood groups AB, BB, BO and AO. What is the blood group of their parents?",
A: "AA and BO",
B: "BB and AO",
C: "AB and BO",
D: "AB and AO",
answer: "C. AB and BO",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question43",
question:  "43. A sick baby was successfully transfused with blood from the father who has blood group AB; what is the blood group of the sick baby?",
A: "A",
B: "B",
C: "AB",
D: "O",
answer: "C. AB",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},

{
id: "question44",
question:  "44. What is the genotypic ratio of carrier female to normal males in the cross?",
A: "1:1",
B: "2:3",
C: "3:4",
D: "4:1",
answer: "A. 1:1",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question45",
question:  "45. Which of the genotypes are carriers of colour blindness?",
A: "I and II only",
B: "I and III only",
C: "Il and III only",
D: "l, II and III only",
answer: "A. I and II only",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question46",
question:  "46. Scientists who study genetics are known as",
A: "genealogists",
B: "geneticists",
C: "mendelists",
D: "genescientists",
answer: "B. geneticists",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question47",
question:  "47. Which of the following scientists did not contribute to the development of genetics?",
A: "Wilhem Johnson",
B: "Thomas Morgan",
C: "Gregor Mendel",
D: "Felix Durjadin",
answer: "A. Wilhem Johnson",
correctLetter: "A",
correctOption: 1,
},

{
id: "question48",
question:  "48. Which of the following terms is associated with natural selection?",
A: "Adaptive radiation",
B: "Differential reproduction",
C: "Population variability",
D: "Survival of the fittest",
answer: "D. Survival of the fittest",
correctLetter: "D",
correctOption: 4,
},

{
id: "question49",
question:  "49. In which of the following insects is group instinct not displayed?",
A: "Soldier ants",
B: "Cockroaches",
C: "Honeybees",
D: "Termites",
answer: "B. Cockroaches",
correctLetter: "B",
correctOption: 2,
},

{
id: "question50",
question:  "50. The inability of an organism to adapt to its habitat can lead to",
A: "dormancy",
B: "adaptation",
C: "extinction",
D: "survival",
answer: "C. extinction",
correctLetter: "C",
correctOption: 3,
},


]